The Rect Transform is a new component that replaces
RectTransform は新規作成される UI 要素で
the usual transform component on all
従来の Transform コンポーネントの
new UI elements.
代わりに使われるコンポーネントです
Whereas the transform component represented the position,
これまでの Transform コンポーネントはシーンにある 3D オブジェクトの
rotation and scale of a 3D object in the scene volume.
位置・角度・スケールの値を保持していましたが
The Rect Transform represents a 2D
この RectTransform は
rectangle specified by a width
幅・高さ・オブジェクトの中心位置を備えた
and a height related to a pivot point.
2D 矩形（長方形）です
Even though the rect transform represents a
RectTransform はシンプルな 2D 矩形で
simple 2D rectangle, the component
表示されるものの
does include a position along the Z axis
オブジェクトの位置として Z 軸や
as well as rotation and scale
角度とスケールなども扱えるので
so the element can be manipulated in the scene
シーン内で 3D オブジェクト的に
volume as a 3D object.
操作することもできます
One important difference between a rect transform and
RectTransform と従来の Transform には
the traditional transform component is the
ひとつ大きな違いがあります
concept of anchors,
それは「アンカー」という概念です
A rect transform can be anchored to it's parent
親子オブジェクトが両方とも RectTransform を持つ場合
if that parent also has a rect transform component.
子を親にアンカーすることができます
Anchoring allows the UI element to move
アンカーされたオブジェクトは 親 UI 要素の
or stretch based on the position and size
RectTransform に指定された位置やサイズに基いて
of the parent UI element's rect transform.
同様に移動・伸縮されます
It is worth noting that all UI elements must
UI 要素はすべて Canvas の子にしておくのが
ultimately be the child of a canvas,
理想的です
even if they are not immediate children.
直子でなくてもかまいません
Canvases themselves have a rect transform.
Canvas 自体も RectTransform を含むため
So in almost all circumstances the parent
通常はすべての UI 要素の親オブジェクトが
of a UI element will also have a rect transform.
RectTransform を持つことになります
And the UI element will be anchored to it's parent in some way.
つまり基本的に「すべての UI 要素は親にアンカーされる」わけです
For more information on the canvas component
Canvas コンポーネントに関する詳細は
please see the information linked below.
下記リンク先の情報をご覧ください
In the Scene view, to manipulate a UI element
シーン ビューで UI 要素を操作する時は
it is best to use the Rect tool.
Rect ツールを使うのが便利です
The Rect tool can be selected by clicking on
Rect ツールは左上のツールバーで
the Rect Tool button in the toolbar.
Rect ツール ボタンをクリックすれば使えます
or by using the shortcut key T.
ショートカット キー T を押しても同様です
With the Rect tool selected it is possible
Rect ツールでは UI 要素の
to move, resize and rotate any
移動・リサイズ・回転など
UI element with that one tool.
様々な操作が可能です
With the UI element selected it can be moved
UI 要素を移動するには まず対象を選択して
by clicking anywhere within the rectangle and dragging.
矩形をクリック & ドラッグします
The UI element can be resized by
UI 要素をリサイズするには
clicking on any of the edges or corners and dragging.
矩形の端や角をクリック & ドラッグします
Note how the cursor changes when hovering
カーソルを注意して見てください
over an edge or corner from the usual pointer
矩形の端や角の上では 通常のアイコンではなく
to a double arrow aligned with the direction
ドラッグした時のリサイズ方向を示す
the UI element will resize when dragged.
矢印アイコンに変化しています
Holding the Shift key will force the UI element
また Shift キーを押しながら UI 要素をドラッグすると
to be resized proportionately.
比率を維持したままリサイズできます
The UI element can be rotated by clicking and
UI 要素を回転させるには
dragging outside of the rectangle near any of the corners.
矩形の少し外側をクリック & ドラッグします
Note how the cursor changes, indicating when the
この場合もカーソルが「回転」を示すものに
tool can rotate the UI element.
変化します
Resizing or rotating a UI element is
UI 要素をリサイズ/回転させる場合には
done in relation to it's pivot point.
ピポット位置に意識する必要があります
The pivot point is very much like the centre
ピボット位置とは一般的なゲームオブジェクトの
point of a standard game object.
中心点にあたるもので
The pivot point is indicated by a blue ring
青色の輪として表示されます
which by default starts in the centre of the UI element.
デフォルトでは UI 要素の中心に配置されます
The pivot point can be moved by clicking and
ピボット位置を移動する場合は シーン ビューで
dragging on the pivot point indicator in the scene view.
青色の輪をクリック & ドラッグします
It is worth noting that the pivot point does not need
なおピボット位置は UI 要素の矩形よりも
to be inside the rectangle of the UI element.
外に配置することも可能です
Placing the pivot point outside of the UI element's
ピボット位置を矩形外に配置すると
rectangle can be done for specialised behaviour.
独特な振る舞いを実現できますが
This however is not a common situation.
一般的には 矩形内に配置します
Another difference between the transform component
RectTransform と transform のもうひとつの
and the rect transform is the effective
大きな違いとして 編集中における
global and local space on editing.
グローバル/ローカル空間に対する影響範囲があります
When editing UI elements in local space
UI 要素をローカル空間で編集している時
the rectangle and handles are aligned with the UI element.
矩形とハンドルは UI 要素に合わせた位置で表示されますが
In global space the rectangles and handles are aligned globally
グローバル空間においては矩形とハンドルの位置がグローバルになり
and the rectangle indicates the bounds of the UI element.
矩形は UI 要素の境界線を示します
This is most notable when the UI element is rotated.
UI 要素を回転させていると 違いが分かりやすいでしょう
In the scene view, anchors are indicated by
シーン ビュー上でのアンカーは小さな三角形を 4 つ輪状に
by four small triangles, which by default
並べた姿で表示されます 位置はデフォルトで
are grouped together in the centre of
親 RectTransform の UI 要素に
the UI element's parent rect transform.
グループ化されます
This parent rect transform can be the canvas.
この親 RectTransform は Canvas にすることができます
Anchors will be covered in detail later in this lesson.
アンカーの詳細については このレッスンの後半で紹介します
When looking at the rect transform in the inspector
さて RectTransform をインスペクターで見てみると
it is clearly different from the transform component.
Transform コンポーネントと明確に違う点があります
The position and size of the UI element are shown
RectTransform では UI 要素の位置とサイズが
in the upper right of the inspector for the
インスペクターの右上に
rect transform component.
表示されるのです
Position shows the distance in pixels
Pos X と Pos Y はアンカーから
from the anchor point to the pivot
ピボット位置までの距離（ピクセル単位）で
along the X and Y axis.
示されます
The position Z is the distance along
Pos Z も同様に距離ですがローカルの Z 軸に
the local Z axis and is often left at a value of 0.
沿っており 通常は 0 になります
Width and Height indicate the size of the UI element in pixels.
Width と Height は UI 要素のサイズを示します（ピクセル単位）
The Position and Size fields are dynamic
位置とサイズは動的なフィールドで
and context sensitive.
状況に応じて変化します
These will be covered in more detail in this lesson
これらはアンカー位置と直接的な関係があるので
as they relate directly to the position of the anchor.
レッスン後半で より詳細な内容を取り上げます
The rect transform component includes a
RectTransform コンポーネントには強力な
powerful anchoring mechanism.
アンカー メカニズムが備わっており
Rect transforms can be anchored to their parent
親ゲーム オブジェクトが RectTransform を含む場合は
if the parent game object also has a rect transform component.
子 RectTransform を親にアンカー付けできます
In most cases, every UI element
通常すべての UI 要素は
will be anchored to it's parent in some way.
何らかの形で親にアンカー付けされます
In the scene view the anchors are represented by
シーン ビュー上でのアンカーは小さな三角形 4 つの
four small triangle gizmos.
ギズモとして表示されます
Each triangle represents one anchor.
この三角形はそれぞれ アンカーを示し
And each anchor is associated with one
RectTransform のそれぞれの
corner of the rect transform.
角に関連付けられています
The upper left anchor is associated with the
左上のアンカーが関連付けられているのは
upper left corner on the rect transform,
RectTransform の左上の角
the lower right anchor to the lower right corner.
同様に 右下は右下 と
This is the same for each anchor and each corner.
各アンカーは対応する角に関連付けられています
Anchors are positioned within the bounds of the
アンカーは親の内側に配置します
parent's rectangle, not the UI element's rectangle.
UI 要素の内側ではないので注意してください
Anchors cannot be positioned outside of
またアンカーは親の矩形の外側には
the bounds of the parent's rectangle.
配置できません
Anchors can be moved by clicking and dragging
アンカーの移動は クリック & ドラッグ操作で
on the triangle gizmo.
行います
Clicking in the centre of a group of triangles
中心部をクリックすると
will move the triangles as a group.
すべての三角形をグループとして移動し
Clicking on an individual triangle will move one anchor at a time.
いずれかの三角形をクリックすると 対象アンカーだけを移動します
Anchors have a fixed relationship to
アンカーはアンカー先の RectTransform に対して
their rect transforms, which they are anchoring.
固定関係にあります
Anchors have a flexible relationship to their
一方で 同じくアンカー先の
parent's rect transform, which they are anchoring to.
親の RectTransform との関係は固定ではありません
When setting an anchor, the distance between
アンカーの設置時
the anchor and the associated corner of
アンカーとそれに対応する RectTransform の角との距離は
the rect transform is a fixed value.
固定値として指定されますが
The anchor's position within the parent's rect transform
親の RectTransform 内でのアンカーの位置は
however is relative to the parent's size
親のサイズに対する相対距離です
and is affected by changes to the size
このため親のサイズが変更されると
in the parent's rect transform.
それに合わせて影響を受けます
The anchor's position relative to the parent is
親に対し相対的なアンカーの位置は
a percentage of the parent's size
X 軸と Y 軸への比率で
along the X and Y axis.
示されます
And it's absolute position can change when the
このため親の RectTransform が変更されると
parent's rect transform changes.
アンカーの絶対位置は変化することになります
This percentage is represented by a normalised
比率は正規化された値で
value from 0 to 1 along each axis.
各軸 0～1 の範囲で指定します
Where 0,0 is in the lower left
0,0 は親 RectTransform の左下
of the parent's rect transform, and 1,1
そして 1,1 は
is in the upper right.
右上を意味します
Practically, this means if all four anchors
通常は 4 つのアンカーすべてが
are grouped together around a single point
ある一点にまとめられているので
the UI element will be anchored to that point.
UI 要素全体がその一点にアンカーされます
If the parent rect transform changes in size
たとえば RectTransform のサイズが変更されても
the UI element will move along with the anchor.
UI 要素はアンカーに合わせて移動するだけで
The UI element will not stretch or resize
縮小/拡大またはリサイズされません
as the distance from the anchors to their associated
これはアンカーとそれに関連付けられた角との距離が
corners is fixed.
固定だからです
If, however, the anchors are separated in any way
逆に アンカーが一点に集まっていない場合は
the UI element will stretch along with the parent
親の変形に合わせて UI 要素も伸縮します
as the anchors, and the space between them,
これはアンカー位置およびアンカー間の距離が
are relative to the parent's rect transform
RectTransform に対して相対的であり
and will change in size if the parent changes in size.
親のサイズ変更を受けてサイズが変わってしまうためです
How much the UI element stretches compared to
この場合 親に対する UI 要素の伸縮比率は
it's parent depends upon the placement of the anchors.
アンカーの位置によって変化します
A few common cases are:
いくつか一般的な例を挙げると:
positioning the anchors are the corners of the UI element,
「アンカーを UI 要素の四隅に設置」
in which case the stretch will maintain the
こうすると 伸縮しても親に対する子 UI 要素の
UI element at the same percentage area of the parent.
表示比率が一定に維持されます
Positioning the anchors at the bounds of the parent.
「アンカーを親の四隅に配置」
In which case the space between the edge of
こうすると UI 要素の端から
the UI element and the bounds of the parent
親の境界線までの距離が
will remain the same, creating a fixed border.
一定に保たれます
Positioning a pair of anchors grouped together
「アンカーを 2 個一組にして
at the edges of the parent's rect transform,
親 RectTransform の角 2 つに配置」
in which case the UI element will stretch
こうすると UI 要素が平行方向にだけ伸縮し
horizontally but not vertically.
垂直方向は固定になります
The stretching behaviour of an anchored UI element
アンカー付けされた UI 要素がどのように伸縮するかは
can be quickly tested by grabbing the edge
親 RectTransform の境界線をドラッグして
of the parent's rect transform and dragging it.
手軽にプレビューすることができます
Note the preview label that appears when dragging,
ドラッグ中はカーソルに「Preview」と表示されます
dragging and note that the parent rect transform snaps
Preview 表示中はサイズをどのように変更しても
back to it's original state when the dragging ends.
ドラッグを放した瞬間に 元の状態に戻ります
To make editing easier, when positioning anchors by hand
アンカーを手動配置するときには
holding the Shift key will change the UI element
Shift キーを押しながら操作すると UI 要素も
size as well.
同時に変更されるので便利です
How the rect transform is resized depends upon the
RectTransform をリサイズした時の挙動は
position of the anchor compared to it's associated corner,
アンカー位置とそれに関連付けられている角の関係によって変わります
as the distance between the two is a fixed value.
これは 両者の距離が固定値であるためです
It is important to note a change in the way
なおアンカーがグループ化されていない状態で
the rect transform displays the positioning
RectTransform の位置/サイズ情報が
and size information when the anchors are
表示されている場合は アンカーの位置として
not grouped together, and no longer define
単一地点が定義されなくなるので
a single point as an anchor.
注意しましょう
When all four anchors are grouped together
たとえばアンカー全 4 個がグループ化されている場合
they define a single anchor point.
アンカーは単一地点として扱われます
And the rect transform displays the positional
このとき RectTransform には
offset from the pivot, and the width
ピボット位置までの距離補正値と
and height of the UI element.
UI 要素の高さと幅が表示されます
When the anchors are split apart however,
しかし アンカーがバラバラの場合は
the rect transform displays the fixed
RectTransform には左右上下に対する
values of the left, right, top and bottom.
固定値が表示されます
These are the fixed offsets, along the X and Y axis
この値は  関連付けられた角に対する
of the anchors to their associated corners.
アンカー位置の固定補正値（X 軸/Y 軸）です
If any two anchors are grouped together
また アンカーが 2 個ずつグループ化されている場合は
there will be no stretching along that axis
対応する軸の伸縮が行われなくなり
and the rect transform will continue to display
RectTransform の表示は対応軸に合わせて
the position and width, or position and height
位置と幅または 位置と高さ
for that axis.
になります
When setting the pivot and anchors for a UI element
UI 要素のピボット位置とアンカーの構成には
there are a number of very common configurations.
一般的なものがたくさんあります
To make setting these quick and easy
そういった一般的用途をすばやく使えるよう
the rect transform includes the Anchor Presets window.
RectTransform には Anchor Presets ウィンドウがあります
This can be accessed by clicking on the
プリセットを使うにはこのボタンを
Anchor Presets button.
クリックします
The anchor presets button displays the current
すると RectTransform の現在の
anchoring choice of the rect transform.
アンカー設定が表示されます
In the anchor presets window there is a set of
このウィンドウでは一般的な
common configurations for the anchors and pivots.
アンカー/ピボット位置構成が指定できます
These common configurations are arranged
構成の並び順は
in the matrix based on the position of the anchors.
アンカーの位置ごとに並んでおり
With fixed anchor points in the middle,
中央部には固定アンカー構成が
and stretch options along the outer edge.
外縁には伸縮アンカー構成があります
The anchor position can be set simply by
アンカー位置はクリックするだけで
clicking on the desired configuration.
簡単に変更できます
Additionally, the pivot, the position of the UI element,
また構成の編集中には UI 要素のピボットと位置の
or both, can be set at the same time
どちらも同時に指定できます
as setting the anchors by holding down
指定するには Shift/Alt キーを押しながら
the Shift and/or Alt keys
指定する構成を
when clicking the desired configuration.
クリックします
These optional keys are noted at the
なお使用できる修飾キーは
top of the anchor presets window.
Anchor Presets ウィンドウ上部に記載されます
Pivot defines the pivot point of the UI element
Pivot は UI 要素のピボット位置を定義する項目で
using a normalised value of 0 to 1
0～1 の範囲で正規化された値を使用します
along the X and Y axis
値はそれぞれ X/Y 軸に対応しており
with 0,0 in the lower left
0,0 が左下
and 1,1 in the upper right.
1,1 が右上を意味します
Rotation defines the rotation of the UI element.
Rotation は UI 要素の回転を定義します
In the most common of cases rotation will
一般的な用途では
only need to be done along the Z axis,
変更するのは Z 軸だけにして
keeping the UI element in 2D space.
UI 要素を 2D 空間内に収めます
Rotation is allowed on all 3 axis however,
Rotation では 3 軸すべてにかけられますが
and the element can be viewed in 3D space.
その場合要素は 3D 空間で見えるようになります
Before discussing scale it is important
スケールについて触れる前に
to understand the difference between scaling and size.
まずスケールとサイズの違いを説明しましょう
When adjusting a UI element's size
シーン ビューで UI 要素の
in the scene view, or adjusting the width and height
サイズを調節したり インスペクターで
in the inspector.
高さ/横幅を調節すると
The UI element is being resized, not scaled.
その UI 要素は「スケール」ではなく「サイズ変更」されます
Resizing changes the rect transform's width and/or height,
サイズ変更した場合 RectTransform の幅と高さが変更され
but does not scale the UI element.
UI 要素のスケールは変更されません
When the UI element is resized
そして UI 要素のサイズを変更しても
this will not effect the font sizes,
対象のフォント サイズや
the border on sliced images,
スライス画像の境界線
or other items related to the UI element.
その他関連項目は影響を受けません
When the UI element is scaled however
一方で UI 要素のスケールを変えると
the entire element is scaled,
要素全体にスケールがかかり
including items like fonts and borders.
フォントや境界線を含めすべてが影響を受けます
For layout purposes it is generally recommended
レイアウト調整の場合は 一般的に
to resize a UI element rather than scale it.
UI 要素のサイズを変更し スケールはそのままにします
Scaling on the other hand can be useful
スケールが便利なケースは
for animated effects or other special purposes.
アニメーション付きエフェクトなど別の用途です
It is worth noting that a UI element
なお UI 要素のサイズに
will become invisible if given a negative size.
負の値を指定すると不可視状態になります
Negative scaling however is supported
他方 スケールは負の値をサポートしていて
and can be used for effects, including flipping the
演出効果として使えます たとえば UI 要素を
UI element with a scale of -1.
スケール -1 でフリップさせる といったように
The rect transform component includes
RectTransform コンポーネントには
two optional editing modes.
この他 2 種類の編集モード
Blueprint mode and Raw Edit mode.
Blueprint モード/Raw Edit モードがあります
Blueprint mode allows for the editing of
Blueprint モードでは RectTransform を
rect transforms as if they were not rotated or scaled.
回転やスケールがかかっていないかのように編集できます
It is worth noting that the UI element
このため Blueprint モードでは
cannot be rotated with the rect tool when on blueprint mode.
Rect ツールを使って UI 要素を回転させられません
Normally when editing the pivot or anchor values
通常 RectTransform でピボット位置や
from within the rect transform
アンカーを編集しても
the pivot or anchor will move and the
ピボットやアンカーだけが移動して
UI element will remain in place.
UI 要素は移動しません
Just like editing these items in the scene view.
言い換えればシーン ビューでの編集と同じ振る舞いをします
When in Raw Edit mode however,
しかし Raw Edit モードを使用すると
the pivot, or anchor, will stay in place
逆にピボットまたはアンカーが固定されて
and the UI element will move relative to that fixed item.
UI 要素が固定項目に対して相対的に移動します
There are times when a rect transform
RectTransform の一部/すべての値が
will have some or all of it's values
親 RectTransform や
driven by a parent rect transform
レイアウト グループなどの UI 要素に
or other UI component, such as a layout group.
制御されている場合
In these cases some or all of the
RectTransform の一部または
properties of the rect transform will
すべてのプロパティが
be greyed out and uneditable.
編集不可状態になります
When this is the case there will be a note
そのような場合には RectTransform の上部に
at the top of the rect transform indicating
値が別のコンポーネントに制御されている旨を
that some values are being driven by another component.
示すメッセージが表示されます
For more information on the components
RectTransform を制御するコンポーネントの
driving the rect transform
詳細については Unity のドキュメントを
please see the Unity documentation
ご覧になるか 対象コンポーネントの
or the associated Learn lesson for that component.
レッスンを視聴してください